<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true and perfect description, of the last voyage or nauigation, attempted by Capitaine Iohn Rybaut deputie and generall for the French men, into Terra Florida, this yeare past. 1565. Truely sette forth by those that returned from thence, wherein are contayned things as lame[n]table to heare as they haue bene cruelly executed.</title>
            <author>Le Challeux, Nicolas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05211</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842600</idno>
  <idno type="VID">7267</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248574522</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 15347</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S106891</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99842600e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05211)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7267)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 443:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true and perfect description, of the last voyage or nauigation, attempted by Capitaine Iohn Rybaut deputie and generall for the French men, into Terra Florida, this yeare past. 1565. Truely sette forth by those that returned from thence, wherein are contayned things as lame[n]table to heare as they haue bene cruelly executed.</title>
                  <author>Le Challeux, Nicolas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[56] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Henry Denham, for Thomas Hacket, and are to be solde at his shop in Lumbart streate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1566]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The authour to his friend" signed: N. le Shalleux.</note>
                  <note>Publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The last voyage to Terra Florida.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B-D.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Ribaut, Jean, ca. 1520-1565 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Florida --  History --  History --  To 1565 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7267:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7267:1"/>
            <p>A true and perfect de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription, of the last voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age or Nauigation, attempted by Capitaine <hi>Iohn Rybaut,</hi> deputie and generall for the French men, into <hi>Terra Florida,</hi> this yeare past. <hi>1565.</hi> Truely sette forth by those that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned from thence, wherein are contayned things as la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mētable to heare as they haue bene cruelly executed.</p>
            <p>JMPRINTED at London by Henry Denham, for Thomas Hacket, and are to be solde at his Shop in Lumbart streate.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:7267:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7267:2"/>
            <head>The Authour to his friend.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Emembring the promes that I made vnto you when we did embarque or take shipping in this Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, for to accōplishe the viage of <hi>Florida,</hi> that, at my returne, if that the Lord God did permit me to returne, I would bring you newes from thence. And althoughe that since my returne, I haue often ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes deuised with you: yet notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, I thought good to doe a thing more agreable vnto you, to set forth in writing so much as I coulde well remember, and that for two reasons. One is, for that I knowe that you loue to heare published the greate wonders of God, which hath bene founde greate in thys discourse, when that shall be sene, the great daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers that he hath deliuered vs oute off, and hath of his mercy graunted vs to sée our owne natiue Countrey. The other
<pb facs="tcp:7267:3"/>is, for that you shall gladlye heare tryed, the inconstancie and variable estate of humaine kinde, wherein his hye looke be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing abated, he learneth to call to God, as it appertayneth to magnifie hys high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, to walke vprightly in his obedience and seruice. You shall vnderstand (friend) to what end I speake this. The erperiēce sheweth, that it is a daungerous thing, when that not contented with our voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, we are drawen backe from our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires, we do that that God defendeth, yea, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> which is nothing necessary. For what nedeth the handy crafts man to leaue his shop, the housholder his deare wyfe, his swéete children, his countrey, his owne &amp; proper goods, for to go seke false &amp; straūge thinges, seking to take shadowes, being guided by blinde guides. But euery one will touch felicity, the which can not be without the meanes of externe goods, yea euē so as is desputed in the schole of that great Philosopher <hi>Aristotle.</hi> I confesse it on condition, if you will graunte that that is verye little, wherewith nature is contented, and that reason demaundeth,
<pb facs="tcp:7267:3"/>but the couetousnesse is greate &amp; gapeth continually. Nowe we poore men at the least, ought to thinke on that which <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> sayth.</p>
            <q>
               <l>That not onely he that possesseth much is happy,</l>
               <l>But he that the giftes of God can vse wysely,</l>
               <l>He whom pouertie holdeth let him paciently beare,</l>
               <l>He that seareth death is neuer the neare.</l>
               <l>He that is cōtēt &amp; prayseth fortunes state,</l>
               <l>Let him not shrinke at all, though she hir wings do beate</l>
               <l>He that seketh not to clime vp fortunes wheele,</l>
               <l>But is content with his estate, muche good thereby shall feele.</l>
            </q>
            <p>O how often is it come to my remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, during this perilious voyage, of that that I haue learned of <hi>Plinie,</hi> of one <hi>Gyges,</hi> that was the rychest of his tyme, how that he, being before the Oracle of <hi>Apollo,</hi> for to enquire of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> most happiest of men. The miscrable proud man vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood otherwise than the Oracle gaue an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> it was a poore olde man named <hi>Aglaus,</hi> which remayned in a corner of <hi>Arcadia,</hi> labouring and tilling a verye little ground which he had, and notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, it rendred ynough to sustaine
<pb facs="tcp:7267:4"/>his lyfe and his family, and being cōtent with this kinde of lyfe, couetousnesse and desire of gaine coulde not once moue him to go out of his little Village: so that he hauing this benefite, was an occasion to auoyde many euilles, and to receyue the lesse sorrowe and bitternesse during his life, louing better his presente estate, than to desire otherwise, and more estée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming his condition than the estate of Kynges. As for mée I am nowe bent to this opinion, that you ought well to note, that the harme that maye chaunce in a mans house during his absence, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong his wyfe and family, doth surpasse y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> pleasure of triumph, which victory doth promisse. For what profited it to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> king of kings (for so <hi>Homer</hi> calleth him) to haue in ten yeares conquered &amp; gottē the moste richest Region of his time, when that at his retourne, he founde his house chaunged and altered, the hearte of his wife rauished by the conceptions of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oultery (beholde the fruite of his voyage) he loseth his lyfe, his sonne banished, and retourning from his banishment, killeth
<pb facs="tcp:7267:4"/>his mother, and the wicked fornicatour that kepte hir, it had bene better for him then, that went to vnpeople <hi>Troy,</hi> and to take by force <hi>Yllion,</hi> to haue taried at home with his wife <hi>Clytemnestra,</hi> thā to haue let a wicked man in his absence oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupie his roume, and entise his wife to euill. Likewise of <hi>Helena,</hi> which bicause of hir husbands absēce, was rauished by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> amorous <hi>Paris:</hi> of <hi>Penelope</hi> which was required of so hote burning louers, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lest that the prudente and wise warriour <hi>Vlysses,</hi> trauayleth the seas to finde out his country. It is therefore our partes, that haue bent our cares to Iesus Christ Lord of our soules, &amp; who alone ought to raigne in our consciences, to obey to his commaundementes, the which is, that a man should cleaue to his wife, and be to hir as glewe, for so haue I vnderstoode of our Doctours, that the worde doth sound <hi>Cula</hi> in the Hebrewe tongue. Morcouer, God cōmaundeth that the husband shuld render to his wife vnfayned loue &amp; good will, but what is the remedie when that they are seperated. I knowe that instlye,
<pb facs="tcp:7267:5"/>we haue felt y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> rygor of Gods iudgemēts: yea for many causes, and principally, for leauing our families, the which we ought to care for most of all, next to God. Let them go to <hi>Florida</hi> who list, for my parte I would not wishe, that that man, that is a houshoulder, should so leaue his occupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for to séeke his aduēture in a straūge countrey, &amp; for a greater profite of gaine: what faire promysse so euer is made of his enterprise. Also, we haue borne the wrath and anger of God, as ye may sée in this discourse of <hi>Florida,</hi> which I do pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent vnto you, desiring you to receyue it as a token or pledge of my good will and loue, the whiche this fiftene yeares hath helde our heartes, straightly lyncked and ioyned together by Iesus Christ our Lorde, to whom alone appertay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the rule, power &amp; glory, for euer and euer. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>At Déepe <date>the .xxij. day of May. <hi>1566.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your louing brother and friend N. le Shalleux.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:7267:5"/>
            <head>¶ Of Terra Florida:</head>
            <head type="sub">or a memoriall Hystorie of that which hath happened in the last voiage by Capitaine Iohn Rybaut, enterprysed by the Kinges commaundement, at an Iland of the Indies which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly is called Florida.</head>
            <div n="1" type="book">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He king with manye Princes and Lords of his counsel, before that y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> tumults and troubles of the Ciuill warre did ryse in his Realme, was minded to sende a competent number of men, with many shyppes, into one of the Countreys of <hi>India,</hi> named <hi>Florida,</hi> new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye discouered and knowē by the French men. Wherefore after that this Cyuill tumult was appeased and published, by his Maiesties authoritie, the pretended
<pb facs="tcp:7267:6"/>purpose cōtinued. And for the executing of this enterprise, <hi>Iohn Ribaut</hi> a man of heart and of counsell, and well séene in nauigation, was sence for to the Court, and there receiued the kings commission to appoint seuen shippes, that might car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye thyther, men, vittayles, and muniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of warre, honouring him with the tytle of Lieutenant, or generall of all the men of warre, the which he had cōmission and commaundement to presse and take vp, expedient for such an enterprise. And to him it was expressiuely defended, to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to lande in any other Countrey or Ilande there, specially in any that is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the dominion of the king of Spaine, but y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> in sayling the great Occean Sea, he should kéepe his full course to <hi>Florida.</hi> The newes of this voyage was soddenly spredde all abroade, and many were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded to submit them selues to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement of this Capitaine, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the kings auctoritie, being led with diuers affections: for some were pricked forward w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> an honest desire for to knowe and sée the Coūtrey, hoping that the sayd
<pb facs="tcp:7267:6"/>nauigatiō would profite them afterward. Others being desirous both with hearte and to minde, make warre, came thither also, louing rather to abide the rage of the waters, than to remaine in their wō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted estate and condicion, the which occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siō might aswell prouoke one as another. The rumor that was spredde here, was: <hi>Florida</hi> promised sufficiencie and conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, of al that man might desire in the worlde. For as much as that countrey re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued a singuler fauour from Heauen, for that there is neither Frost nor Snow of the coldenesse of <hi>Septentrion,</hi> nor yet the burning heate of the South. The fiel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des without labouring and tilling, bring forth inough, wherewith to sustaine the lyfe of men that dwell or shall dwel or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habit there. It séemeth for to make a coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey the moste fruitefullest, and rychest that is in the compasse of the worlde, if that there were men that woulde employ their industrie or diligence, in trimming of the ground to mans vse, the which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth from <hi>Aquilon</hi> to <hi>Septentrion,</hi> almost in the like longitude, as <hi>Europia,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7267:7"/>and his latitude is .xxiii. degrées. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times whē y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> the beames of the sunne are spredde from the highest degrée, it recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth great heate, the which notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, is tēpered not onely with the fresh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of the night, or with the Dewe that falleth from heauen, but also with moste gracious raine falling aboundantlye, so that the ground is very fruitefull, yea, in such sort, that the grasse groweth of a wō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull highnesse. It is also rich of golde, and with all sorts of wylde &amp; tame beasts, which haue the fieldes fayre and large. Notwithstāding also, the Hilles are of a reasonable highnesse, the Flouds and Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers very pleasant, dyuers kinde of trées rendring swéete smelling sauour. All this being considered, it coulde no otherwise be, but that man there shoulde haue great pleasure, and singuler delectation. Many therfore being ouercome with these faire promises, others with a couetous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire, thinking to be made ryche by this voyage, bicause of the gold, came by hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes to this towne, where y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> mnster should be, for to choose those, which at the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:7267:7"/>of the Kinges Lieutenant, shoulde séeme most fitte for the beforenamed en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprise: but it was not so soone put to effect as some did desire, &amp; specially those that had receiued the souldiers into their Innes and houses, for they were wery to haue men that made suche chéere, wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out paying the shotte, though that they promised them with assurance that short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye they shoulde be contented and payed. And they were foure Monthes and more in thys Towne or euer they set forward. But in the ende, they were bounde by a certain othe, to behaue them selues faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully in the kings seruice, receyuing wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges for six Monthes, which at the last, was not to the Generals contentation. For about the Moneth of May. <hi>1565.</hi> that againe the muster of men shoulde be for to take shipping, some of them that had receyued wages, being troubled in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science, of so long a voyage, being also a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed to beholde the rage of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Sea, chaū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged their purpose, and withdrewe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues secretly, without passing any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Nowe for to make shorte, and least
<pb facs="tcp:7267:8"/>they should dayly diminish, they were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine instantly called and, they were cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded that at that verye houre, they shoulde take shipping, which was the tenth day of May, &amp; we remayned in the Rode, till the .xxij. day of the before sayde Moneth, tarying for certaine beastes and corne. The number of men for this voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age were thrée hundreth, besides handy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craftes men &amp; their families. And whylest that we stayed for the commaundement and commoditie of our Lieutenant, and hauing the wind fauourable, the Tuesday being the .xxij. day of May, there did ryse a great tempest, the windes blowing vs from one parte to another, in suche sorte that the waues meting, with such a vyo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent force, gaue such feare to our Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, that they could find no other proper remedy, but to cut the Cables, leaue the Ankers, and to giue vs ouer to the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of the winde. The moste violentest winde that was, was a Northerly winde, the which draue vs so swiftly, that soden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we were at New Hauen, and there we remayned thrée dayes, loking for newes
<pb facs="tcp:7267:8"/>from Déepe by a Bringandine, that we sent straightly thither, and then we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared oure selues, to departe from this Rode, the .xxvj. of the beforesaide Month, &amp; as we thought to kepe our right course, incontinently a contrary winde tooke vs, and caused vs to retire to the Ile of Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kam, one of the Countreys of England, where the English men were desirous to know of our enterprise, &amp; after y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> they had knowledge therof: they offred to doe vs pleasure. The daye that we arriued thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, was the .xxviij. of May, and there we did ride at an Ancker till y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> .xiiij. of Iune, on the which day, we had the winde at the Northeast as faire as we did wish, so that we hoyssed vp our sayles, and say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the right course to <hi>Florida,</hi> the which we did long to sée, and we remayned say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the greate <hi>Occean</hi> Sea, two whole Monthes, before that we could haue sight of <hi>Terra Florida,</hi> sauing of an Iland, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Pesants <hi>Vocaionques,</hi> some of our mē would haue named this Ilād <hi>Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therine</hi> by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> name of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Quene, mother to the King: &amp; they sayd, that it is .xxvij. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grées,
<pb facs="tcp:7267:9"/>of latitude. We sawe also a shippe two hundreth Leagues beyond, towards the Sea, but we came not nere it, by thre or foure Leagues. When that we were aryued into <hi>Terra Florida,</hi> we perceyued the flers that the <hi>Indians</hi> made vs, which was the .xiiij. day of August. We sente a Erigandine to discouer a little Ryuer, and at the mouth of the Riuer, there were certain wilde mē, which did trucke siluer for our marchādise that we had brought, and they saide that they had that siluer, of a shippe that had bene cast away, cōming from <hi>Entailes.</hi> We found there a certain Spaniarde, escaped from a shipwracke twentie yeares agoe, whome we tooke vp into our Brigandine, and we did inquire of him, if he coulde tell any newes of the Frenche men, that kepte a holde in that Coūtrey: and he answered that he knew nothing, sauing y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he vnderstoode of those wilde men, that they were encamped fifty Leagues more Northwarde than where as they were aryued, so we set vp sayle and coasted al along y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> coast, which semed to be the sandy lande, planted with little
<pb facs="tcp:7267:9"/>trées all along, and the floudes that come from the Southwest are there very smal, and in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> mid way we discouered a Ryuer, that our men before tyme had named the Ryuer of <hi>May,</hi> whereas also the floudes are not very greate that come from the North northeast. And bycause of the shallownesse of the waters, we might sée the Anker holds y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> before had bene there, and we founde within thrée or foure Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues of lande, six or seuen fadome water, or there about. I remēber also, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> betwene the Ryuer of <hi>May</hi> &amp; another named <hi>Aye,</hi> we founde another on the Northe syde, about two Leagues distant from the Ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of <hi>May,</hi> and there we cast Anker be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing benighted, hauing cyght or nine fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome water, finding the bottom in some places sandy, somtymes grauely, &amp; much <hi>Oxias.</hi> We sounded also y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Ryuer of <hi>Dol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phins,</hi> and there we found at the bar two fadome, but at a full Sea there is sound two fadome and thrée quarters. And after that we had long coasted the coast to find a landing place, the .xxvij. day of August, we cast oure Ankers in the Rode, of the
<pb facs="tcp:7267:10"/>Ryuer of <hi>May,</hi> at seauen fadome water, being frō the lande about two Leagues. On Wednesday being the .xxix. of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sayde Moneth, we entered into thrée Barges, &amp; rowed vp the sayde Ryuer, straight to the holde where oure men kepte, the whiche they before time had made, for their place of assurance and rest, a place very cōmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious, as well for the Ryuer that it hath on the one side, &amp; a wood on other y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> side, which is distant not passing a quarter of a myle from the place, and a fayre fields betwene the wood and the Holde, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other side verye pleasaunt couered with grasse and hearbes, very long, and of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers kinds: and there is no way into the Wood, sauing a little way made by oure men, about a mans pace, the which they had made in going to the fountaine that was in the sayde wood. When that we were aryued nere to the sayde place, our Lieutenant caused the vittayles to be dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged, &amp; carryed to the Holde, with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther munitions to recreate y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> place, and also commaunded, that we handycraftes men with our wiues and children, should
<pb facs="tcp:7267:10"/>go thither, and caused vs to be condutted thyther by a Gentleman of the house of <hi>Vlly,</hi> of <hi>Beauchaire,</hi> and others, to whome also he gaue the charge of his most precious cariage. Those that taryed for vs at the Fort, were greatly reioysed at our comming, for they were perplexed and troubled to be so long tyme without hearing any newes out of France, and that more augmented there dolour, they were without vittayles, vnlesse that they would accustome them selues to liue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the order of the Countrey In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitantes, of whom also they could get nothing, but by violence and force, as we shall declare more plainelye hereafter. Nowe when that we were remayning there, I cōsidered the forme of the dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of the lande, which séemed to me good and gentle, for the men are straight and well proporcioned, somewhat of a ruddy colour. I vnderstoode that in euery village they haue a king, and for their clothing they haue Lether marked after a strange fashion, they haue no apparell neyther men nor women, but the women are gir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb facs="tcp:7267:11"/>with a little valle or apron of the skin of some beast, for to couer the parte of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that is most shamefast. Thei are nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther flat nosed nor great lipped, but their face is rounde and full, their eyes cleare and feareful, their haire is very long, and they trusse it very properly round aboute their heades. And this trussing of their haire serueth them in stede of a Quiuer, to carry their arrowes when they goe to warre: it is maruellous to sée how sodē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye they haue them ready in their handes to shoote very farre and as streight as is possible. As touching their maners, they are dissolute, they instructe not their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, neyther yet correcte them, they wyll take without conscience, and al that they can catche secretlye, they counte it their owne. Euery one hath his owne wyfe, and they kepe maryage, yea, with all Ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor. They warre against the Countryes adiacent, which are of diuers languages. Their weapons are bowes and arrowes. Their houses are rounde almoste like a Doue house, founded and established with great trées, couered ouer with leaues of a
<pb facs="tcp:7267:11"/>Palme trée. They feare not the windes and tempestes. They are often grieued with little flyes, which in their language they cal <hi>Maring<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ns,</hi> and it behoueth them ordinarily to make fiers in their houses, specially vnder their beddes, to be dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered of this vermine. They say that they sting cruelly, and that part that is tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with their stinging, looketh lyke the fleshe of a lazar. They estéeme nothing so rich and so faire as the feathers of Birds, being of dyuers colours. They estéeme muche little counters, that they make of the bones of certain fishes, &amp; other grene stones and redde. Their foode is rootes, fruite, herbes, and fishes of diuers kinds, and their fish is very fatre that they hang to drye, the which they call in their lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage <hi>Boquarie,</hi> they take out the fat the which they vse in stéede of butter &amp; saulse. They haue no corne, but they haue aboū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of a certaine séede which groweth y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> heigth of seuē foote, his stalke is great like a Cane, and the graine great like a pease, the eare is a foote long, the colour is of the colour of wax vnwrought: the meane
<pb facs="tcp:7267:12"/>to vse it, is firste to bruse it and stampe it to meale, then afterwarde they vndoe it by mingling and make therwith their Mygan, which is like to Rice that is kept in this countrey. It must be eaten assone as it is made, bycause it will quicklye chaunge, for it is not to be kepte. They haue many bastarde Ʋynes growing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout trées, as we sée in some Countreys of this Realme, but they haue not the vse to presse out the Wine. Their drinke they call <hi>Cassinet,</hi> is made with hearbes mingled together, and séemeth of the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of Ale of our countrey, I haue tafted thereof, and it hath not bene straunge to me. As touching the countrey it, séemeth to me hilly. There are many Forrestes which maye be the occasion of so manye wilde beastes, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> which they say will hurt those that take not good heede. I wil leaue to speake many things of wilde beastes, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> which only I haue heard speake of, but it is inough for me to wryte that which I haue séene, and that séemeth to me wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of memorie for the posteritie. And singulerly of Cocodrils, the which often
<pb facs="tcp:7267:12"/>tymes are séene come forth of the sande to go séeke their pray, we haue sene many, specially one deade, and we haue eaten thereof, the which eateth tender, &amp; white as veale, and almost of the same taste. He was killed with the shotte of a Gunne, stroken betwéene two skales, otherwyse they are strong inoughe for any strokes: his mouth very great, &amp; his téeth straight like the téeth of a combe, his body was .xij. or .xiij. foote long, the legges very short to the proportion of the bodye, his nayles straunge and cruell, his tayle strong and long, wherin consisteth his life and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall defence. Also in the mouth I find no apperance of tongue, for he had the vpper parte vnder, a thing monsterous, whiche in beholding thereof is inoughe to giue feare to men. Also I did sée a serpent dead by the wood which had bene killed by one of our men, of which the wilde men cut of the heade, and did carry it away with greate care and diligence: I coulde not know the reason wherfore they did so. He had wings by the whiche he might some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes flye vp from the ground. Some of
<pb facs="tcp:7267:13"/>our men thought that the wilde men did it for some superstition, and as farre as I could sée, they are not without some opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of diuinitie, like as I do coniecture by certaine circumstances, that easelye they might be brought to good ciuilitye and honestie, and also to holinesse &amp; sound Religion, if that God of his mercy would vouchsafe it: for so soone as the Bell had rong for to goe to prayers of our Holde, they would be there, and stretch vp their handes to heauen as we did, yea, with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence and attentiue eare. In y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> meane time, our gouernor was by for to acquite faithfullye his charge, and gaue order that the holde might be so ramperde and furnished, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> it might serue for a defence, least by aduēture y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> barbarous mē might sodenly make an insurrectiō, &amp; ouerrunne vs. Monday the third day of September, did ariue nere to our shippes fiue sayle of Spanishe ships, the Admiral being of the burthē of .iiij. hūdreth Tunnes, the Barke a hūdreth &amp; fiftie Tunnes, being followed with thrée patences, the which came &amp; cast Anker hard by our shippes about nine of
<pb facs="tcp:7267:13"/>of the clocke towarde night, in the night they and our shippes spake together, and when that our men had asked them why they came to séeke them, they aunswered that they were enimies, and that the war was sufficiētly declared, so then our men beholding the strength of the Spaniards to their enuy and naughtye will, wayed their Ankers, and set vppe sayle, and the Spaniardes chased after them, but they coulde not get them by sayling, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they retired into the Ryuer of <hi>Dol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phins,</hi> and there they were minded to des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cende. And after that they had conspired our ruine with the wilde men, as y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> issue of their enterprise in the ende sheweth, from this Ryuer they sente of their men by companies as many as they thought néedefull for to execute their enterprise. And since we vnderstoode of the wylde men, that they were in armour sixe hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dréth men. Not long after, thrée of oure shippes being come againe to the Rode, (for the Trinitie our Admiral was borne downe the Riuer hauing no Anker holde) the Capitaine <hi>Iohn Rybaut</hi> was myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb facs="tcp:7267:14"/>with these thrée shippes to pursue the Spaniards: and after that he had coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sailed with his men vpon this enterprise, shewing vnto them that it was necessary to shewe their force vpon the water, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse they would incurre the losse of their shippes, for our men being on lande could not let them to effray those that were left in the shippes, being but a small number in comparison to the enimies, the which seemed vnto vs an intollerable losse, spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially that we coulde sende no cōmoditie into France for to let the kings Maiestie vnderstande the estate of our enterprise. Therefore vpon Monday the tenth day of September, thrée houres before noone, the Capitaine and kings Lieutenant would sée all his men, and after that he had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted them to do well in the Kings ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, toke shipping with them, taking for his defence not onely the Souldiers that he had newelye brought thither, but also the best of them that kept y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> place before, also the chiefe standard of Capitain <hi>Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duniere.</hi> This Capitaine being weryed without hearing newes out of Frauce,
<pb facs="tcp:7267:14"/>and displeased for that he was depriued of foode, a little before y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> we aryued thither, thought to returne againe into France, and in the meane time did not care much if his company did that to the Countrey Inhabitants, wherby their good affection might be turned from the Frenche men, but he suffered them to force them and bring them prisoners to their Holde, to take by force their Mill, and other things that necessitie, whiche can bée vnder no law, did constraine them. And for so much as desire of vengeance is naturally plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in mannes heart, also that the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon appetite of all beastes is to defende their bodyes and lyues, and to auoyde those thinges that shall séeme hurtefull, it is not therefore to be doubted, but that these wilde men did confederate with the Spaniards, how they might be deliuered of vs French men, with whom they were both in body and goodes trauayled &amp; pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. The Tuesday being the .xj. of Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember, aboute eight of the clocke in the morning or there about, when that oure Capitaine was very nere to the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards
<pb facs="tcp:7267:15"/>there did rise a great wind which cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued a long tyme, with great showers of raine, thunders &amp; lightnings, in such sorte that the ayre was some tymes like fyre, so that both partes being afrayed of the rage of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> weather, seperated our thrée shippes, being faine to abide the weather, and the Spanish shippes made the winde good: and the rage of the weather dured till the .xxiij. day of September. Now the Spaniards being descended on land, had leysure enough to espie &amp; séeke out a way vnto the Holde, and to inuent the meanes howe to entrappe vs, knowing that our General was at sea with y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> chiefe strēgth, looking for fayre weather, and that those that remayned in oure Holde were the most part sicke, being altered by the smel of the Sea, part handycraftes men with women and children, being in all to the number of two hundreth &amp; forty soules, vnder the garde and diligenee of Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Lauduniere,</hi> which misdoubted no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing lesse, than that a companie might come by lande to entrappe them. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Capitaine did rise earely in the
<pb facs="tcp:7267:15"/>morning for to refreshe him, bycause of the foule weather that had bene y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> nighte before, opening the wicket an houre be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Sunne rysing, the most parte of vs in the Holde being fast a sléepe and in our beddes. The Spaniardes hauing tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersed Woods, Dytches and Ryuers, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conducted by the wylde and barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous men, aryued the Monday being the xx. day of September, in the morning earely to our Holde, the morning being very cloudy and rayny, and entered ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in without any resistance, whereas they made a most horrible and dolefull slaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of our men, such a rage and crueltie they had conceyued against our Nation. They sought then who could best cut the throtes of men, hole &amp; sicke, women &amp; litle children, a pitisull sight and lamentable. Some of our men, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> most nimblest, step<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping out of their beddes, got away and sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them selues in the shippes that were in the ryuer, being left there by our Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, vnder the keping of <hi>Iames Ribaut</hi> Capitaine of a shippe named the Pearle, and vnder <hi>Luis Ballard</hi> his Lieutenant:
<pb facs="tcp:7267:16"/>the others being almost intrapped, leaped ouer the fence or wall of our Holde, the Capitaine <hi>Lauduniere</hi> saued him selfe by that meanes, with hir that serued him in his Chamber. I was almost taken soden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye going to my worke, my toole in my hande, for comming out of my Cabane, I met the enimies, so that I knewe no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meanes to escape, but to turne my backe and hye me as fast as was possible to leape ouer the fence or wall, for I was coursed with a Pike man, and I knowe not how otherwise but only by the grace of God, my strength doubled poore olde man that I am &amp; gray headed, notwyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stāding I leaped ouer the Ramper, which in taking aduisement I coulde not haue done, for it was eight or nine foote highe, so that when I was ouer, I hasted to saue me in the Woods, and about the distance of a bowe shoote, when that I was néere to the Wood, I turned my face towarde the Holde &amp; stayed a little, and that more holder for that no man followed me. And as from the place where I stode, I might easely sée the Holde, so did I heare an hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible
<pb facs="tcp:7267:16"/>cry of the slaughter that was made af our men, and thrée auncients of oure aduersaries planted vpon the Rampers. Hauing now lost all hope to sée our men together, I put my selfe into the mercye of God, and launched into the thickest of the wood, for this I thought, that I should not finde more greater crueltie among the wylde beastes, than the crueltie that the enimies extended vpon our men. The miserie and trouble wherewith I felt my self wrapped, seing in earth no more hope but that the lord God of his speciall grace aboue mannes hope might deliuer me, it made me therfore cast sighes and teares, and with a voyce full of sorrow I began to cal vnto God after this fore, saying: O God of our fathers and Lorde of all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solation, which hath commaunded vs to call vpon thée euē from the laake of Hell and panges of death, promising thy so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine ayde and helpe, shewe vnto me, for the hope that I haue in thée, what way I might take for to come to the ende of this miserable age, plonged in the gulfe of sorrow and bitternesse, at the least cause
<pb facs="tcp:7267:17"/>me that féeling the effect of thy mercy, the assurance that I haue conceyued in my heart of thy promises, be not taken away by the cruelty &amp; furious rage of the wilde beasts on the one side, and of thy enimies and ours on the other side, the which séeke our death more for that thy holy name is called vpon amongst vs, than for any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing. Helpe me O god, assist me, for I am so aflicted that I can call no more.</p>
               <p>And in the meane time whilest I made this discourse, trauesing the Wood very thicke of Brears and Thornes, vnder the hyghe trées where as there was neyther pathe nor way, wherein I had bene not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the space of halfe an houre, but that I hearde a noyse, as though it were the wepings and complaintes of men that were aboute me: notwithstanding, I going forwarde in the name of God, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing confidence in his helpe, I discouered one of oure companie named <hi>Lasieur</hi> of <hi>Blonderie,</hi> and another behinde him, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med mayster <hi>Robert,</hi> being well knowen of vs all, for that he had the charge to say seruice in oure Holde, shortely after
<pb facs="tcp:7267:17"/>came to vs the Lackeys of <hi>Le Sieur de Vlly,</hi> the Nephewe of <hi>Mounseur Beau,</hi> Master <hi>Iames Teuse,</hi> and many others. So being gathered together, we did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sult of our miseries, deliberating of that which we had to do for the sauing of our liues. And amōgst vs one being somwhat séene in the Scriptures, began after this maner, saying: Brethren, ye sée in what extremitie we are, what parte soeuer we turne our eyes, we se nothing but barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rousnesse, the heauen, the earth, the sea, the woods, the men, &amp; to be short, nothing fauoureth vs. What knowe we if that in yelding vs to the fauor of the Spaniards, they wil shew fauour. Wel, yet although they kill vs, it shall be suffered but for a time, they are men, and it may be that their fury being appeased, they will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue vs on composition, otherwise what should we do, is it not better for vs to fall into the handes of man, than into the mouthes of wilde beastes, or rather to die for hunger in a straunge lande. After that he had fayde these wordes, the most parte of oure companye was of his aduise, and
<pb facs="tcp:7267:18"/>praysed his counsell. Notwithstanding that I shewed them the crueltye, yet all bloudy, of oure aduersaries, and that it was not only for one cause and humaine debate that they had executed with such a fury their enterprise, but principally for the knowledge that hath bene giuē them, that we are of those that are returned to the preaching of the Gospell: let vs not the refore be so wilfull as to trust in man more than in God, which maketh those that are his to liue, yea, euen in the midst of the dead, and giueth alwayes his helpe when that the hope of man fayleth. Also I did alleage certaine examples oute of the holy Scripture for the purpose, of Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seph, Daniel, Elias, and other Prophets. Also of the Apostles, as of S. Peter, and of S. Paule, the which all, being brought out of affliction, yea, by extraordinarye meanes, and straunge to the sense and reason of man, his arme I say is not at al weakened, his hande is alwayes one. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member ye not (saide I) howthe children of Israell fledde from Pharao, what hope had this people to escape the handes of
<pb facs="tcp:7267:18"/>Tyrant mighty and cruell, he followed them euē hard at their héeles, before them they had the red sea, on both sides mighty hye hilles, what then, he that opened the sea for to make a way for his people, and afterwarde swallowed vppe the enimies therin, might not he in like maner guide vs through the woods and fieldes of this straunge Countrey. For all that I could say, sixe of the company followed the first preposition, and left vs, taking their way to their enimies, hoping to finde fauour and grace before them, but they knew in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continently and by experience, what folly it is to trust more in mē than to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of our god. For being once come forth of the wood, as they thought to haue gone to the Fort, beholde they were taken by a cōpany of Spaniards, and intreated like vnto the others, they were killed, &amp; then drawen to the Ryuer side, whereas the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers being slain in the Holde lay on hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes. And I will tell an exāple of extreme cruelty. <hi>Iames Rybaut</hi> capitaine of the Pearle, rid with his shippe at an Anker about a hundreth paces from the Holde,
<pb facs="tcp:7267:19"/>and receyued many of those that escaped this slaughter. The Spaniards hauing their hearts great, bicause of their victory, were bent to dispatch the rest of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Frēch men, made ready the ordinance against the shippes and boates, but bicause of the raynie weather, and for that the Gunnes were oute of order, they did no harme to our men, but they sent a Trumpet vnto them to summō them to yelde, but when they sawe that this feared them nothing, they sente one of their men euen vnto the Shippes, shewing the authoritie of <hi>Dom Pedre Maluendo,</hi> generall of their company, for to compound with our men on this condition, that they shoulde leaue the shippes and goe their wayes in their Boates with their baggage to the other shippes that were more lower at y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> mouth of the Ryuer, distant from the Holde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout two Leagues, to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> which our men aunswered, that there was no warre be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene them, when that aboute sixe Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes passed, they had receyued commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of the King to make this voyage, so that we haue not enterprised to do any
<pb facs="tcp:7267:19"/>wrong or exaction to any man, for it was expressiuely defended by his Maiestie, &amp; also of his Admyral, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> we should make no discent in any part of Spaine, nor yet to come neare, for feare of offending them. We haue kepte and obserued the kinges commaundemēt inuiolately, so that you can not saye against vs, that we are the cause of this slaughter y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> you haue made of our men, against all vsage of warre, the whiche maketh our hearts to bléede, for the which dede you may hereafter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in tyme and place, féele. And as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the shippe that you demaunde, you shall sooner haue our lyues, and whereas you thinke to constraine vs, we will em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy the meane that God &amp; nature hath giuen vs to defende vs. The Spaniarde being returned backe, did report that our men feared them nothing, but that they were minded to stande to defence. Then this furious company cast the coller and bloudy dispight vpon the deade bodyes, and shewed them to the French mē that rested vpō the water, so that they sought to hurt the soules of them of whome they
<pb facs="tcp:7267:20"/>woulde if that they coulde dismember the body, for pulling out the dead mens eies, they did sticke them on their Dagger poyntes, and then with exclamations, cauntes, and mockings, threwe them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde the Frenche men that were vpon the water. As for vs that remained in the woods, we continued trauesing, keping to out iudgement the right course to the Sea. And as it pleased God to direct our steppes and adresse our wayes, by and by we came to the croupe of a hill, and from thence we perceyued the Sea, but for all that there was great distance, and that worsse was, the way that we had to take séemed maruellous straunge and harde. Firste the Mountayne whiche it beho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vs to discende downe, was of such a heygth and so slope, that it was not possible for any man keping him on his legges to descend, so that none of vs durst descende but for the hope that we had of certaine shrubbes and Brears that grew on this hilles side, by the helpe of which we gat downe, not without great paine, in scratching and renting our hands and
<pb facs="tcp:7267:20"/>our legges, yea our bodyes also being all bloudy. Being descended from the hil, we lost sight of the Sea by reason of a little wood that was planted before vs, and for to goe to the wood, it behoued vs to tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uesse a great field being marish ground, wherin did grow many wilde Roses and other straunge hearbes, of which the stal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes being harde as wood, and the leaues, cutte our féete and our legges euen to the bloude, being alwayes in water vp to the knées, and that that doubled our miserie and calamitie, was, that the raine did fall from heauen in such sort, that we were as betwene two waters, and the farther we went, the deper we found y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> water. Then thinking that we were come to the laste end of our life, we embraced one another, and with a common affection we began to sighe and crye vnto the Lorde God, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusing our sinnes, and knowing vpon vs the rygor of his iudgements. Alas O lord God (sayde we) what are we any other than pore wormes of the earth, our soules being altered and chaunged with sorrow and griefe, doth yelde them into thy han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des<pb facs="tcp:7267:21"/>O Father full of mercy, and God of Charitie, deliuer vs out of this place of death, or if thou wilte that in this deserte we make an ende of our liues, assist vs O Lorde, that death which of all things is most terriblest, when he commeth to take holde of vs, that he feare vs not, but that we may remayne firine &amp; stable in minde of thy fauour and good will that we haue so many tymes tasted on and approued in thy Sonne Iesus Christ, for to giue place to the spirite of Sathan, the spirite of dispaire and defiaunce. For be it that we dye, we protest nowe before thy Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lestie, that we wil die to thée, be it that we liue, it shall be to tell of thy maruellous workes, in the middest of the congregatiō of thy Saintes. Our prayers ended, we went forwarde with great payne to the wood, in so much that we arriued nere to a great Ryuer that ranne throughe the midst of this fielde, the breadth was not very great, but very depe, and the water ranne with great swiftnesse, for so much as this fielde was not farre from the sea. This Ryner was an other increasing of
<pb facs="tcp:7267:21"/>our sorowes, for there was not one of our men that durst swim ouer the Riuer. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in this confusion of thoughts how to passe ouer, Iremembred the wood that we left behinde vs. After that I had er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted my brethren to patience, &amp; to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in good hope of Gods mercy, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to the wood and cut a long piece of wood with an ende of a Bill that was left in my hande at the houre that the Holde was taken, I came againe to the others that taryed me in great perplexitie. Now brethren, sayde I, let vs see if that God by this staffe will shewe vs fauour to bring our iourney to an ende, so we layde the staffe or forke vpon the water, one of our men, and also euery one following his turne, holding it by the end, and entring into the water caried the forke with him, and in the midst of the water, as we lost the sight of it, we pushed it with force and strength to the other side wheras we toke lande, with the helpe of the Réedes and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hearbes that grew on the brinke, and so we passed all one after another, but it was not without great daunger, &amp; drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb facs="tcp:7267:22"/>much salte water, yea, such a quan titie, that comming to the other side, oure heartes fayled vs, &amp; we were as one that is halfe drowned. After that we were come to our sclues, &amp; had taken courage, tending alwayes to the wood, the which we had marked to be nere to the Sea, the forke also was necessary to passe an other arme of water, whiche gaue vs no lesse paine to passe than the first, but thankes be to God we passed it, and towarde the night, we entered into the Wood, where we remayned all the night in great sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe and feare, standing vpright oure backes to the trées, and for all our greate trauayle &amp; iourneys, yet we had no mind to sléepe, for what rest could the spirites haue being in such fears? Also we saw a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the poynt of day a beast, greate, lyke vnto a stagge, within fiftye pases of vs, whose heade was very bigge, the eies fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, the eares hanging, hauing y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der partes indifferent. She séemed vnto vs verye monstrous bycause of hir eyes, whiche séemed as thoughe they were fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, being very great, the which came
<pb facs="tcp:7267:22"/>not neare vs, for to doe vs anye harme. The day being come, we came out of the woode and then we sawe the Sea for the whiche we had wished so much, nexte to god, as an only meane to saue our liues: but we were againe troubled, for we saw it all a marish ground full of water and couered with briars &amp; wilde Roses like to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> which we trauessed the day before. We went forward trauessing these marishes, and neare vnto the place where as wée were mynded for to goe, we perceyued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the wylde Rosiers a companie of men, which at the first sighte we thought had béene our enimies which were come thither to curte our waye, but when that we had behelde more neare, we saw that they were desolate &amp; naked as we were, by the which we knew that they were of our men, for there was the captaine <hi>Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duniere,</hi> his chamber mayd, <hi>Iames Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gens</hi> of Déepe, and <hi>Fraunces Duuall</hi> of Roane, with many others to the number of .xxvi. persons, vpon the deliberation of that which we hadde to doe. One of oure men clymed vpō one of the highest trées,
<pb facs="tcp:7267:23"/>where hée discouered one of oure little shippes whiche was vnder the charge of captaine <hi>Mailarde,</hi> to whome they gaue a signe, by the which they vnderstoode our néede: so he caused his little barke to come neare, but to approch the sea banke it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houed vs to passe through these wilde ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, and two little ryuers like vnto those that we had passed the daye before, to the which was very necessarie our pearch or Forke that I had cut the day before, and other two that Captaine <hi>Lauduniere</hi> had made prouision of, so that we came nere ynough to the Bark, but our hearts say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vs, what for hunger and trauaile. So that we had remayned there, had not the Mariners holpen vs, which shewed them selues verye succourable: and they bare vs one after another into their Barke, and so caryed vs to their shippe, whereas we were well and chéerefullye receyued. They gaue vs breade and water, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that we had eaten, we began by little and little to receyue strength, which was a most sure token of Gods mercy, who had saued vs, againste the hope of infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite
<pb facs="tcp:7267:23"/>daungers of death, with the whiche we were compassed on all sides, for to rē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vnto him meste heartie thankes and prayse for euer. So we passed the nighte talking of the miraculous workes of god, and comforting one another in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of our deliuerie. The day being come, <hi>Iames Rybaut</hi> Capitaine of the Pearle, bourded vs, for to conferre with vs what were best to be done, for to saue the rest of our men and shippes, and then it was shewed the scarcitie of vittayles that we had, our strengthes broken, oure munitions of warre in our enimies han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, the vncertain estate of our gouernor, not knowing whither the rage of the tē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pest had driuen them. We concluded ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that we coulde doe no better than to assay to returne into France, and y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest of our company were of this aduise, to seperate in two partes those that were escaped from the Holde, and that some of them should be in the Pearle, and the rest vnder the charge of Capitaine <hi>Mailarde.</hi> So on Thursday being the .xxv. of Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember, we parted from the coast, by the
<pb facs="tcp:7267:24"/>fauour of a Northerly winde, minding to sayle into Fraunce. And since the first day oure shippes were so parted, that we met no more vpon the seas together. We sayled .v. hundreth Leagues happely, but in a morning before the Sunne rising, we were assayled of a Spanishe shippe whom we susteyned to our powers, &amp; we so beate him with Gunne shotce, that we made him yelde to our willes, &amp; we beate him in such sort, that the bloud ranne out at the skupper holes, so that no man was sene aboue hatches: but we could not bord them bycause of the weather, for feare of brousing our ship. They also being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, let vs goe, &amp; so we left them, thanks be to God, and ioyfull of that which had happened, and for that none of vs was hurte nor killed in this fight, sauing oure Cooke. The rest of our nauigation hath bene without meting of our enimies, but we haue bene sore weather beaten, and almost driuen on y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Spanish coast, which had bene an increasing of our sorrows, &amp; the thing that we did most abhorre. We haue also endured on y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Seas many other
<pb facs="tcp:7267:24"/>things, as colde, and hunger. For you shall vnderstande, that we that were es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caped from <hi>Terra Florida,</hi> had no other apparell left, neyther for the nighte, nor yet for the day, but one poore shirt, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other little thin thing vpon it, which was very little to defende vs from the iniurie of the weather, and that worsse was, the breade that we did cate, was fenoed and naught. Also the fresh water that we had, did stinke, of the which we had all the day long, but one taster or smal cup ful. This naughty and corrupt nourishment is the cause, that we being descended a shore, are fallen into so many kinds of diseases and sicknesses, the which hath caused to dye a great many of our company. And at the end of this perillous and lamentable na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uigation, we were dryuen on the coast of Rochell, whereas we haue bene gently intreated of the inhabitants of the Coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and of those of the towne, giuing vs of their goods so much as necessitie requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, being assisted of their good willes, we had sufficient for euery one to returne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Countrey.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="book">
               <pb facs="tcp:7267:25"/>
               <head>The seconde booke.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>E haue hearde howe Capitaine <hi>Iohn Rybaut</hi> tooke shipping with y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers for to finde out the Spaniards, and so hauing sought them the space of fiue dayes, and not finding them, he met the Admirall of his fléete, named the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, and being minded to kepe the coast against the Spaniardes, not knowing of that which had happened at the Holde, entered therein, according to the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie custome. The weather was trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blesome, for that the winde blewe so ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely, and it rayned continually. The fift day the tempest encreased after suche sorte, that they were not able to resist it, but of force were dryuen to the shore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the Ryuer of <hi>May</hi> about fiftie Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues, and there the ships were broken, and their munitions lost, notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the men came on lande, sauing the Capitaine <hi>Grange,</hi> which caste him selfe
<pb facs="tcp:7267:25"/>vpon a mast and was drowned, a man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the others much to be lamented, as well for the good counsell that he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes gaue, as also for the fruites of his amiable acquaintance. Our men being then saued on shore from the rage of the waues, found them selues wrapped in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother trouble, for to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> hunger that helde them, there was no remedy, vnlesse they woulde eate suche thinges as the earth brought forth, that is to wit, hearbes, roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and suche like, with the which they thought to satisfie their crauing stomack. There was not neyther to satisfie their thirst, but olde Cesternes wherin the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was much troubled, for the skum that it did cast, to loke to was enough to make a whole body sicke, notwithstanding, the rage of their extreme hunger and thirste caused them to digest these vnholesome meates and drinks, which semed to them very strange, and they were in this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexitie the tearme of eyght dayes. The ninth day by fortune they founde a little Barke, for the which they were somwhat comforted, hoping by that meanes to let
<pb facs="tcp:7267:26"/>them of the Holde vnderstande of their shipwracke. Now betwéene them and the Holde it was .xij. Leagues by lande, and fiftie by water, and betwéene them and the Forte was the Ryuer of <hi>Dolphins,</hi> which is very depe, and of the breadth of one quarter of a Mile, wherfore without some vessel, it was vnpossible for them to passe ouer. When then they had receyued this Barke, they did caulke it with their shirts in stede of <hi>Okum.</hi> Then y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> capitaine <hi>Iohn Ribaut</hi> of his grace and accusto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med modestie, called many to his counsel and said vnto them after this fort: Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions and friendes, it is not for vs to continewe our lyues in such miserie and calamitie, it were better for vs to wishe for death, than to liue being charged with suche afflictions, vnlesse that God of his grace hath giuen vs fayth of his proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence for to looke for succour, suche as it shall please him to sende vs, and in the meane time, let vs employ oure minds to séeke out the issue of these troubles. I am of this mind, that there be some amongst vs, the which shall go to the Fort in this
<pb facs="tcp:7267:26"/>litle Barke, for to let our men vnderstād oure extreme néede, to the ende that they giue vs succoure, and being on the shore casting out many teares, they began to call vpon the name of God knéeling on their knées. When their prayers were finished, they beganne to looke, which of them were most aptest to sende: and they named <hi>Thomas Le Vasseur</hi> of Déepe, to whome Captaine <hi>Iohn Ribaut</hi> gaue the charge, that assone as he could, he should let them of the Forte vnderstande their distresse, and with him there went <hi>Vyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Symon, Michell Gouer,</hi> and others to the number of sixtene. Our men, as I sayd before, were on the contrary side of the holde, for the riuer of <hi>Dolphins</hi> was betwene thē and the holde, so that going forwarde on lande toward the Fort, they sawe the very same day, on the other side of the riuer, a cōpany of men of Armes with their Standerds spread, &amp; after that they had known by coniectures that they were Spanyards, our Frenchmen were perplexed in their heartes, knowing not what to doe, but for their best remedye,
<pb facs="tcp:7267:27"/>they sent some of their cōpanie swiming ouer the riuer for to make offer to yelde, their liues saued. The swimmers were receyued at the first very curtcously, the Captaine of this Spanish company was named <hi>Vallemande,</hi> who sware by the fayth of a gentleman &amp; christian knight, to vse his good will towarde the French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, also that it was the order alwayes practised in warre, that the Spaniard be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing victorious, should be contēt, specially with Frenchmen, without attempting further, and he shewed vs also by signes, to the ende that we might be persuaded of this fayre promisse, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> herein we should finde no fault, that the nations hereafter shoulde not speake thereof. And inconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nētly he caused a Barge to be made rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye, into the which he commaunded fiue Spaniardes to enter to passe ouer oure mē, the which they did. Now this Barge being come to the other side, and that the Spaniardes had made a narration in the name of <hi>Vallemande,</hi> the Captaine <hi>Iohn Ribaut</hi> entered first into the Barge, and others to the number of thirtie, and he
<pb facs="tcp:7267:27"/>was gently receyued of <hi>Vallemande,</hi> but the others that were of his companie were caried further off &amp; all bound, their hands behind there backes, two and two together, so the rest of our men passed ouer by thirtye at a tyme, whylest that <hi>Vallemande</hi> entertayned our good Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Iohn Ribaut</hi> with fayre flattering wordes, the which trusted to the fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full promisse of the sayde <hi>Vallemande,</hi> to whome he had yelded. Now our men as they came ouer, were bound two to two, and being altogether Frenchmen and Spaniardes, they went toward the Fort, the Captaine <hi>Iohn Ribaut</hi> and others, specially the <hi>Sieur</hi> of <hi>Ottigny</hi> when they sawe our men coupled together, began to chaunge countenaunce, and agayne desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the sayde <hi>Vallemandes</hi> fauoure, who assured them, saying that those bāds were only to bring them to the holde in saftie, and that there he woulde kepe that which he had promised. And when they were neare to the holde, he enquired of them whiche were Mariners, Carpenters of shippes, goonners and others which were
<pb facs="tcp:7267:28"/>necessarie to the offices of the Sea, the which being chosē out, were thirty men. And shortly after, beholde a cōpany came from the Holde to oure men, who were made to come behinde the <hi>Sieur</hi> of <hi>Valla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mande</hi> &amp; his companie, like a companie of beastes that are dryuen to the slaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Then with the noise of Drums, Flu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and Trumpets, the courage of these furious Spaniardes was extended vpon the poore Frenchmen which were bound. There was assay who coulde best strike with the Pike, Haulberd and sworde, in such sort, that within halfe an houre they wonne the fielde and name of this glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous victorie, killing those there, most cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elly, which were yelded, and whome they had receyued on their fayth and alleage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. During this crueltie the Capitaine <hi>Iohn Rybaut</hi> made certaine exhortations to <hi>Vallamande</hi> to saue his lyfe. Also the <hi>Sieur</hi> of <hi>Ottigny</hi> knéeling on his knées, remembring <hi>Vallamande</hi> of his fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full promisse, but all was to no effect, for he turning his backe, went a little from them, &amp; then one of his murtherers stroke
<pb facs="tcp:7267:28"/>the Capitane <hi>Iohn Rybaut</hi> behinde with a Dagger, that he made him fall downe, and then doubled his strokes, till that he had taken his life from him. After suche sorte were our men handled, that before vnder the shadowe of assurance made by the Spaniards, had yelded. And for to shewe the more crueltie, they rente the Kings Lieutenants beard in despite, and for a shewe of there expedition, the which shortly after they sente to <hi>Syuell,</hi> as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of our Mariners, reserued for thys voyage, haue few dayes passed faithfully shewed vs, specially one <hi>Chrystopher le Britton</hi> of New Hauen, the which secret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly departed from <hi>Syuell</hi> to the towne of <hi>Burdeux,</hi> and from thence by ship came to Déepe, and for a memorial of their vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie, they quartred the body of this faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full seruant of the King, <hi>Iohn Rybaut,</hi> and of his head made foure quarters, the which they did sticke at the foure endes of the Fort.</p>
               <p>Here haste thou (gentle Reader) séene the discourse of two sorts of people, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thou mayest iudge with indifferencie,
<pb facs="tcp:7267:29"/>and sée what couetousnesse causeth, being both desirous of gaine, and in specially the monstruous crueltie of the one part. But the Historie suffiseth of it selfe, God is a righteous iudge which séeth the actes of all humaine kinde, and shall rewarde euery one according to their deserts. God kéepe vs from murther and bloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shedde, and giue vs grace to feare him, and honour his holy name aright. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:7267:29"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>